# Name: Ciriaka Gitonga

Title/Qualification: PhD

Position: Dean School of Education and Social Sciences/Senior Lecturer

**Area of Specialization:** Educational Psychology

**Contact Address: 16724 00620** 

**E-Mail:** ciriaka.gitonga@embuni.ac.ke or cikagijo@gmail.com

0722 444094

### **Short Biography**

Ciriaka Gitonga (PhD) holds a Doctorate in Educational Psychology specializing in, Educational Psychology and Career Assessments. Dr. Gitonga is a Senior Lecturer and the Dean School of Education and Social Sciences. Dr. Gitonga is an avid scholar is widely published high impact journals. She has been plays various advisory roles in schools policy development and implementation and passionately involved in child protection activities in schools. Currently Dr Gitonga is involved in developing school behavioral intervention plans in Kenya. Dr Gitonga has grown from a high schools teachers, Director of Community Based Institution that provided alternative programmes for youths with borderline disabilities, Director of PAC University Campus, and now the Dean, School Education and Social Sciences, University of Embu. Dr Gitonga loves working in teams and she drives joy from mentoring young adults.

#### **EDUCATION AND TRAINING**

PhD, Educational Psychology: Kenyatta University 2008/2013

**Licenced Career Development Facilitator**: National Career Development Association

(2006/2007);

Advanced Counselling: Association of International School in Africa

(2004)

Master of Education:

Diploma in Human Resource Management:

Bachelor of Education (Home Economics):

Kenya Advanced Certification of Education

Kenya Certificate of Secondary of Education

Certificate of Primary Education

Kenyatta University, (2000/2002)

Kenyatta University (1988/1991)

Chogoria Girls 1986/1987

Machakos Girls 1982/1985

Kagumone Primary School, 1981

#### PROFESSIONAL BODIES/Committee MEMBERSHIP

National Career Development Association Kenya Career Development Association Society of Differently Talented Special Education Technical Committee (2010-2017)

### WORK EXPERIENCE

2018- to date: Dean Lecturer Department of Psychology: University of Embu

**Duties: Teaching** 

### 2014 – 2017: Pan African Christian University

**Duties:** 

Position Director of Quality Assurance and Valley Road Campus

**Responsibilities:** Day to day running of the Campus. Key responsibility is to ensure quality instruction and growth of the Campus.

#### **Achievements:**

- An Accredited Peer Reviewer with Commission for University Education Kenya;
- Widely Published in Career and General Psychology; Inspection by CUE and awaiting report. Enhanced visibility, increased enrolment, and good quality teaching and instruction.
- Directed the Process of Inspection and Accreditation of PAC, University Valley Road Campus 2015;
- Chaired the successful PAC University Commission for University Education Institutional Audit;
- Overseen the development and approval of eight programs in the University
- Established quality assurance directorates and support systems.
- Conducts continuous training program on quality assurance in the University.

# **Committees and Responsibilities**

**CUEs Self Assessment and Evaluation (SARs):** Chaired the committee that prepared and steered the successful university inspection by Commission for University Education in October, 2014.

**Quality Assurance Directorate:** Responsible for the establishment of the quality assurance system in the university. **Achievement**: Senate passing quality assurance guidelines and appointment of relevant of quality and standards sub- committee.

Academic Programs Development Committee: Responsibility: Chair: Steering the committee to ensure that the program developed fully adhere to the CUE Standards and Regulations before submission to CUE. Achievement: Approved programmes Bachelor of Commerce, Bachelor of Business Information and Technology, Bachelor of Business Leadership, Bachelor of Community Development, Masters of Arts in Business Administration, Post Graduate Diploma in Leadership, Bachelor of Counselling Psychology.

Peer Reviewer for Commission for University Education

**Baraton University of East Africa** Institutional Audit (February, 2015) **Karatina University:** Programme Audit (December 2016) **Embu University:** Programme Audit (December 2016) **St Pauls University:** Quality Audit (February, 2017) **EAST Theological University** Quality Audit (February, 2017) Laikipia University: Quality Audit (February, 2017) Programme Review (May, 2017) Kisii University

#### PREVIOUS WORK EXPERIENCE

# Adjunct: Daystar University: Master of Art in Child Development: Supervision of Thesis

# 2009-2014 Director Kenya Community Centre for Learning

Role: Program Director

# Responsibilities

- ♣ Management of Curriculum Delivery and Evaluation
- ♣ Developing and implementing child protection procedures and practices
- ♣ Managing child and family therapy for children with various difficulties
- ♣ Monitoring and evaluating instructional procedures in in the centre
- ♣ Administering and reporting psychological assessment reports
- Managing progress reports of children in difficulties
- **♣** Resource mobilization
- ♣ Vocational and psychological assessment administration

### The Aga Khan Academy, Nairobi

# Title: Career Counsellor and College Placement officer Nairobi 2004-2008

Responsibilities included guiding the student through career decision-making process; selection and placement into Universities locally and internationally; management of internal and external work placement program, administering career assessment inventories and reporting.

# The Kenya Community Centre for Learning, Nairobi

Title: School Counsellor, 2001-2003

## **CONSULTANCY and Funded Projects**

Consultancy: Designing Child Protection Policy (2016- On-going) Consultancy: Inclusive Education Review: Oshwal Academies (2015)

Consultant for International Aids Services: Capacity Building For SASE in Hargeisa

Somaliland in Vocational Development for persons with disabilities (2011-2014).

**Funded Projects:** Establishment of Therapy Center at Kenya Community Centre for Learning: Australian Government (DAP) AusDollar 7000. 2013.

## **Workshops and Conferences**

- **1.** 8<sup>th</sup> KASH Conference 2018: Presented Paper on: Perceived paternal care as a predictor to depressive symptoms among adolescent boys in Kiambu County"
- **2.** The 2<sup>nd</sup> Kenya National Adolescent Health Symposium 2017: Presented paper on: Paternal care as a predictor of depressive symptoms among adolescents boys in Kiambu County.
- **3.** In the Best Interest of the Child International Conference. Daystar University 2016: Presented a paper on "Children with disabilities and access to education: Parenting dilemmas.
- **4.** Decolonizing the Spirit for Education Advancement International Conference: University of Embu June 2016: Presented a paper on: Applying Daily Spiritual Experiences in Education for Persons with Disability

- 5. Oshwal Academy Workshop: Safeguarding and Child Protection: Role: Lead Consultant
- **6.** The 2015 Kenya Association of Private Universities (KAPU). Re-Aligning Academia, Government & Industry (AGI). Roadmap for the attainment of Vision 2030;
- 7. The National Family Conference 2015: The Christian Professional Forum;
- **8.** Institute for Human Development, Aga Khan University: Investigating Early Childhood Development for a Better World. February, 2015;
- **9.** Kenyatta University Postgraduate Seminars: Present research finding for the doctoral studies, Dec, 2013;
- **10.** Daystar University. Summit on the plight of the African child, a Christian Perspective. 25<sup>th</sup> October, 2013;
- **11.** Riara University: Transformational Perspectives in Education in Africa. Presented a paper entitled "Transforming the career potential for learners with disabilities by reforming the career counsellor training". 18<sup>th</sup>-19<sup>th</sup> June, 2013;
- **12.** National Career Development Association: "Building on our Dreams; Atlanta Georgia, USA. June 21<sup>rd</sup> to 29<sup>th</sup> 2012:
- **13.** Career Development Facilitators Instructor Training; June 25<sup>th</sup>-June 27<sup>th</sup> 2012 Maryland USA:
- **14.** Capacity building in Communication skills on Inclusive Education in Somaliland. September, 24<sup>th</sup> to 29<sup>th</sup> 2011. Role: Lead Consultant;
- **15.** Capacity Building in Leadership: Mentoring/Coaching Special Educators Somaliland. Ongoing program: Role Lead Consultant;
- **16.** Capacity Building workshop in Leadership on Inclusive Education in Somaliland June 16<sup>th</sup>-23<sup>rd</sup> 2011. Role: Lead Consultant;
- **17.** Capacity Building workshop on "All in all types of minds in one lesson plan" May 23<sup>rd</sup> 2011 Nairobi. Role: Training Consultant;
- **18.** Vocational Skills development for children with with learning difficulties art exhibition July 28<sup>th</sup> 4<sup>th</sup> August art Exhibition Nairobi: Role: Convenor;
- **19.** Host TV talk show on "Learning Disabilities in Kenya, the role of Parents" 29<sup>th</sup> July, 2011);
- **20.** Capacity building "Understanding the role of psychological assessment in Learning Difficulties" July 13th -16<sup>th</sup> July, 2009. Nairobi: Training Consultant;
- **21.** Host a TV talks show: Are students with learning difficulties persons with disabilities? July, 2010

#### **Professional Bodies Membership**

- 1. National Career Development Association. International Affiliate member
- 2. Career Development Association Kenya, Founder Member 2013
- 3. Special Educational Technical Committee Member

# **Post Graduate Research Supervision**

The Influence of Regulated Marital Conflict	Sarah Njoroge	2015
Resolution Styles on Martial Stability in Kiambu		
County ((Masters Thesis)		

Psycho-Social Effects Of Domestic Violence (Dv) And The Attributions For The Culture Of Silence Among Married Men. A Case Of Nairobi County, Kenya ((Masters Thesis)	Anne Muteti	2015
An Investigation Of How Teachers Lead Preschoolers Into Language Acquisition By Modelling Skills Through Songs In Selected Schools In Nairobi County, Kenya (Masters Thesis)	Thelmer Rimber	2015
Psychotherapy Methods for Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder in Children and Adolescents in Selected Centres in Nairobi. 2015 (Masters Thesis)	John Kangethe (Daystar University)	2014
The Psychosocial Challenges experienced by Sexually Abused Children during Court Proceedings in Kenya: A Case of Makadara Law Courts Nairobi. 2015. (Masters Thesis)	Esther Ngina (Daystar University)	2015
Psychosocial Challenges faced by Children with Reading Difficulties in Upper Primary School. A Case of selected schools in Kitengela, Kajiado County. (2014) (Masters Thesis)	Phyllis Munyi (Daystar University)	2015
The Effects Of Power-Factor On Gender-Based Violence In Marriage Relations: A Case Of Married University Students. 2015 (Masters Thesis)	Pauline Nduati (PAC University)	2014
Psychosocial Risk Factor for Depression Among High School students in Kenya 2014(Masters Thesis)	Prisila Mugambi (Daystar University)	2014
Teachers' Knowledge and Management of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in Selected Primary School, Nairobi Kenya. 2015 ( Masters Thesis)	Terry Chore (Daystar University	2014

# **Publications**

Kuboka, R. & Gitonga, C. (2018). Relationships between Perceived Paternal Care and Depressive Symptoms Among Adolescent Boys in Kiambu County, Kenya. Journal of Advanced Psychology Vol. 2, Pp 1-8, 2018

Mugambi, P & Gitonga, C. (2015). Adolescent Awareness of the Psychosocial Risk Factors for Depression in Selected Private Secondary Schools in Nairobi Kenya. Manuscript submitted for Publication to International Journal of Psychology, July 2015

- Kariuki, N. S., Aloka, J.A., Gatumu, H.N. & Gitonga, C. (2015). Relationship between perceptions of inter-parental conflicts and involvement in Delinquent Behavior among selected Kenyan adolescent students. Journal of Educational and Social Research.Vol.5 ISSN 2239-978X. Doi:10.5901/jesr.2015.v5n1p
- Kariuki, N. S; Aloka, J.A; Gatumu, H. N. & Gitonga, Ciriaka. (2015). Relationship between perceptions of parental punitive discipline and involvement in delinquent behavior among selected Kenyan secondary school students. Journal of Educational and Social Research: Vol 5: Doi:10.5901/jesr.2015.v5n1p
- Gitonga, C., et al (2014). *Is the choice of a degree program a factor of personality type and degree of congruence*. IOSR Journal of Humanities and Social Science, DOI 10.9790/0837-1925495
- Gitonga, C., (2013). Relationship between Holland's Personality Types, Gender, Congruence and Satisfaction with the Choice of Degree Program Among Third Year Students, Kenyatta University, Kenya. Unpublished PHD Thesis
- Gitonga, C., (2013). The Omnipresent Gendered Career Pathways for Women and the Role of Career Counselors in Kenya. International Journal on Science and Research (IJSR). Online ISSN 2319-7064, Vol 2 No, 8.
- Gitonga, C., Kigen, E., Wangeri, T., & Orodho, J. (2013). *Is Congruence a Predictor of Satisfaction with the Choice of Degree Program among University Students in Kenya. Journal of Education and Practice*. ISSN 2222-1735 (Paper) ISSN 2222-288X (Online)Vol.4, No.17.
- Gitonga, C., Orodho, J., A., Kigen, W., & Wangeri, T (2013) *Gender Differences in Holland*. International Journal of Education and Research Vol. 1 No. 7 July 2013.
- Contributor Author on "Christian Perspective and Research on the Child Development on the African Context". Publisher: Daystar University, Institute of Child Development.
- Gitonga, C., Ndisya, W. & Athiende, J., (2013). *Psycho-Educational Assessment for Dsylexia* Kenya Community Center for Learning Publication. In Press.
- Gitonga, C., (2009). "A systematic Guide to Career Choice in Kenya" Integrity Publishers Inc, Nairobi, Kenya.
- Gitonga, C. (2002). Parental Involvement in the academic performance of their children. A case of schools in Egoji Location. Unpublished Masters Thesis Kenyatta University, Nairobi Kenya

# Referees.

Prof. Daniel Mugendi VC. University of EmbuMartin Njoroge vc@embuni.ac.ke Embu